Finding Aid for Sam Breck photograph collection
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sam Breck photograph collection 1950s-1990s
Breck, Samuel L., 1928-
2008032 Aa 2
Sam Breck was an Ann Arbor, Mich., photographer. The collection consists of color slides of railroad depots and other railroad scenes, chiefly in Michigan but including scenes in other states; slides, photographs and negatives of Ann Arbor and University of Michigan buildings, views, and events; photographs and negatives of Michigan Youth Symphony.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Sam Breck (donor 5447 ) in 1998, with an addition donated by his estate, through Bill McKnight, in 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Samuel "Sam" L. Breck, Jr. was born in 1928, the son of Samuel L. and Margaret H. Breck. In 1930 the family lived in Detroit, Precinct 19. Sam also had a younger brother, David. For over 40 years, Sam Breck was married to his wife, Marion. Together they had two sons, Bob and Bill, and three grandchildren. Sam was a photographer, particularly of trains, locomotives, and depots. During the last years of his life he battled a number of illnesses. Sam died on March 15, 2009 in Minnesota. He was buried from St. Andrew's Episcopal Church in Ann Arbor, Michigan. His wife, Marion, preceded him in death. (This information is from his obituary published in the Ann Arbor News on March 29, 2009.)
The Sam Breck photograph collection consists of color slides of railroad depots and other railroad scenes, chiefly in Michigan but including scenes in other states; slides, photographs and negatives of Ann Arbor and University of Michigan buildings, views, and events; photographs and negatives of Michigan Youth Symphony. The collection is divided into four series, based on format: Slides, Prints, Negatives, and Contact sheets, along with a small Other series.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor Train and Trolley Watchers.; Michigan Central Railroad Depot (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Michigan Youth Symphony.; University of Michigan.; Railfans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Railroads--United States.; Railroads--Michigan.; Railroad facilities--United States.; Railroad facilities--Michigan.
Contributors:
Tarbell, Jim.
Genre Terms:
Color slides.; Photographs.; CD-ROMs.
- Slides
  The Slides series includes mainly images of railroad depots, mainly in Michigan but including depots throughout North America. The depot slides are arranged by rail line, in two sequences, Michigan and Miscellaneous. The Michigan Central Depot (now the Gandy Dancer Restaurant) in Ann Arbor is extensively documented. Smaller numbers of slides of other Ann Arbor scenes are also included in this series. Researchers should note that other photographers are credited for a number of the slides.
  - Ann Arbor 1970s (Box 1)
  - Buildings and details (Box 1)
  - Carnegie libraries (Box 1)
  - Dams and bridges (Box 1)
  - Michigan depots
    - Ann Arbor Railroad depots (Box 1)
    - Detroit, Toledo & Ironton depots (Box 1)
    - Grand Trunk Western depots (Box 1)
    - Michigan Central Depot, Ann Arbor, Mich., 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Norfolk & Western depots (Box 1)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad (ex Grand Rapids & Indiana) depots (Box 1)
    - Soo Line depots (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan depot (Box 1)
    - Wabash depots (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous depots (A-Z), 8 folders (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan libraries (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Prints
  The Prints series chiefly includes images of Ann Arbor and University of Michigan scenes: streetscapes and landscapes, buildings, and events. Some railroad images are found in the series, including three folders of the work of Jim Tarbell. Two folders of photos of performances and rehearsals of the Michigan Youth Symphony are included.
  - Ann Arbor
    - Aerial (Box 1)
    - Art Fair (Box 1)
    - Cityscapes, buildings, commercial (Box 1)
      (black & white)
    - Cityscapes (color) (Box 1)
    - Landscapes, parks (Box 1)
    - Residential, churches (Box 1)
  - Building details (Box 1)
  - Chelsea, Mich. May 1994 (Box 1)
  - Churches (Box 1)
  - Country buildings (Box 1)
  - Hillsdale Fair, Hidden Lake Gardens, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Houses (Box 1)
  - "In town" buildings (Box 1)
  - Michigan Youth Symphony (Box 1)
  - Michigan Youth Symphony, Blue Lake 1973 (Box 1)
  - Railroad stations and rail-served buildings (Box 1)
  - Railroads
    - Detroit Toledo & Ironton, Ford Rouge Plant, Ambassador Bridge (Box 1)
      (most by Jim Tarbell)
    - Grand Trunk Western accident at Trowbridge crossing, East Lansing, Mich. December 31, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Grass Lake, Mich. circa 1994 (Box 1)
    - Michigan (Box 1)
    - Michigan (by Jim Tarbell) (Box 1)
    - New York Central at Jackson and Dexter, Mich. (Jim Tarbell) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Ships (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan (Box 2)
    - Band and orchestra (Box 2)
    - Buildings
      - Burton Tower, Law Quadrangle (Box 2)
      - President's House, Angell Hall, West Engineering, Museums (Box 2)
      - Details (Box 2)
    - Campus views (Box 2)
    - Sports (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Negatives
  The folder headings in the Negatives series generally parallel the Prints series, but the collection does not necessarily contain a negative for each print, or vice versa.
  - Ann Arbor
    - Activities and events (Box 2)
    - Buildings (Box 2)
    - Buildings, commercial-churches-civic (Box 2)
    - Cityscapes, streetscapes and residential, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Parks, landscapes, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Residential (Box 2)
  - Carnegie libraries (Box 2)
  - Churches (Box 2)
  - Courthouses (Box 2)
  - Michigan (Box 2)
  - Michigan Youth Symphony (Box 2)
  - Michigan Youth Symphony, Blue Lake 1973 (Box 2)
  - Railroads
    - Michigan (Box 2)
    - New York Central at Jackson and Dexter, Mich. (Jim Tarbell) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Schools (Box 2)
  - Ships (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan
    - Buildings, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Campus views (Box 2)
    - Events (Box 2)
    - Sports and band (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Contact sheets with negatives
  The Contact sheets series contains contact sheets with associated negatives for Ann Arbor and University of Michigan scenes.
  - Ann Arbor (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan (Box 2)
- Other
  The Other series includes a CD-R with images of meetings and outings of the Ann Arbor Train and Trolley Watchers, 1981-1991, and a few miscellaneous items.
  - Ann Arbor Train and Trolley Watchers 1981-1991, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 2)
  - Postcards (Box 2)
  - Transit tickets (photocopy) (Box 2)